<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-2"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "/usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % docvars SYSTEM "../docvars.xml.in">
  %docvars;
]>

<book>
	<bookinfo>
		<title>syslog-ng v2.0 reference manual</title>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Bal&aacute;zs</firstname>
				<surname>Scheidler</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<releaseinfo>&syslogng_version; (&syslogng_revision;)</releaseinfo>
		<copyright>
			<year>1999-2006</year>
			<holder>Bal&aacute;zs Scheidler</holder>
		</copyright>
		<legalnotice>
			<para>This manual is free software; you may redistribute it and/or modify it under the
				terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free Software
				Foundation; either version 2, or (at your option) any later version. </para>
			<para>This is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but without any warranty;
				without even the implied warranty of merchantability or fitness for a particular
				purpose. See the GNU General Public License for more details. </para>
		</legalnotice>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="intro">
		<title>Introduction to syslog-ng</title>
		<para>One of the most neglected area of Unix is handling system events. Daily checks for
			system messages is crucial for the security and health conditions of a computer system. </para>
		<para>System logs contain much "noise" - messages having no importance - and important
			events which should not be lost in the tide of messages. With the current tools it is
			difficult to select which messages are interesting. </para>
		<para>A message is sent to different destinations based on the assigned facility/priority
			pair. There are 12+8 (12 real and 8 local) predefined facilities (mail, news, auth
			etc.), and 8 priorities (ranging from alert to debug). </para>
		<para>One problem is that there are facilities which are too general (e.g.: daemon), and are
			used by many programs, even if they do not relate each other. It is difficult to find
			the interesting bits from the enormous amount of messages. </para>
		<para>A second problem is that there are very few programs which allow setting their
			"facility code" to use for logging. It is at best a compile time parameter. </para>
		<para>Consequently, using facilities as a means of filtering is not an optimal approach. A
			better solution would be to make the syslog facility a runtime option for all
			applications, and add the ability to create new facilities in syslogd. Neither of these
			are available; the first one is not even feasible. </para>
		<para>One of the design principles of <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> was to make message
			filtering much more finegrained. <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> is able to filter
			messages based on the contents of messages in addition to the priority/facility pair.
			This way only the really important messages are sent to a specific destination. Another
			design principle was to make log forwarding between firewalled segments easier using
			long hostname format, which makes it easy to find the originating and the chain of
			forwarding hosts - even if a log message traverses several computers. The last principle
			was a clean and powerful configuration file format. </para>

		<sect1 id="timezone_handling">
			<title>Timezone handling</title>
			<para>One of the new features of syslog-ng 2.0 is the support for messages originating
				from different timezones. This is a difficult problem, as the original syslog
				protocol does not include timezone information. syslog-ng provides a solution by
				extending the syslog protocol to include this information and also by giving
				finegrained control to the administrator to supply timezone information for legacy
				devices which do not support the protocol extension. </para>
			<para>Timezone information is associated with messages entering syslog-ng using the
				following algorithm:</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>The sender can specify the timezone of the messages. If the incoming
						message includes a timezone it is associated with the message. Otherwise,
						the local timezone is assumed.</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>The administrator specifies the <link linkend="sourcecommonopts">
							<parameter>time_zone()</parameter>
						</link> parameter for the source driver that reads the message. This
						parameter overrides the original timezone of the message. Each source
						defaults to the value of the <link linkend="reference_options">
							<parameter>recv_time_zone()</parameter>
						</link> global option. </para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>The destination driver specifies the timezone via the <link
							linkend="destcommonopts">
							<parameter>timezone()</parameter>
						</link> parameter. Each destination driver might have an associated timezone
						value to which message timestamps are converted before they are sent to the
						final destination (file or network socket). Each destination defaults to the
						value of the <link linkend="reference_options">
							<parameter>send_time_zone()</parameter>
						</link> global option. A message can be sent to multiple destination
					zones.</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para> When macro expansions are used in the destination filenames, the local
						timezone is used. </para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
			<para>There is another case when message timestamps are formatted: </para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="msgroute">
		<title>Global objects</title>
		<para>In <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> a message path (or message route) consist of one or
			more sources, one or more filtering rules and one or more destinations. A message is
			entered to <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> in one of its sources, if that message matches
			the filtering rules it is sent to the specified destinations. Note that a message goes
			to <emphasis>all</emphasis> matching destinations by default, although this behavior can
			be changed. </para>
		<sect1 id="sources">
			<title>Sources</title>
			<para>A source is a set of source drivers collecting messages using a given method. For
				instance, there is a source driver for <parameter>AF_UNIX</parameter>,
					<parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> style sockets, used by the Linux
					<filename>syslog()</filename> call. </para>
			<para>To declare a source, the source statement has to be used in the configuration file
				with the following syntax: </para>
			<para>
				<synopsis>
					source &lt;identifier&gt; { source-driver(params); source-driver(params); ... };
				</synopsis>
			</para>
			<para>The identifier has to uniquely identify the given source, and may not clash with
				any of the reserved words (in case of a name clash, simply enclose the identifier in
				quotation marks). </para>
			<para>You can control exactly which drivers are used to gather log messages, thus you
				have to know how your system and its native <parameter>syslogd</parameter>
				communicate. Below is an introduction to the inner workings of
				<parameter>syslogd</parameter> on some of the tested platforms:</para>
			<table>
				<title>Communication method between syslogd and its clients</title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Platform</entry>
							<entry>Method</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Linux</entry>
							<entry>A <parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> unix socket named
									<parameter>/dev/log</parameter>; some of the distributions
								layers switched over to using <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter>,
								though applications still work with either method. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>BSD flavors</entry>
							<entry>A <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> unix socket named
									<parameter>/var/run/log</parameter>.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Solaris (2.5 or below)</entry>
							<entry>An SVR4 style <parameter>STREAMS</parameter> device named
									<parameter>/dev/log</parameter>.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Solaris (2.6 or above)</entry>
							<entry>In addition to the <parameter>STREAMS</parameter> device used in
								earlier versions, 2.6 uses a new multithreaded IPC method called
								door. By default the door used by <parameter>syslogd</parameter> is
									<parameter>/etc/.syslog_door</parameter>. </entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			<para>Each possible communication mechanism has the corresponding source driver in
					<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>. For instance, to open a unix socket with
					<parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> style communication use the driver
					<parameter>unix-dgram</parameter>, the same with
				<parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> style - as used under Linux - is called
				unix-stream. </para>
			<example>
				<title>Source statement on a Linux based operating system</title>
				<synopsis>
					source src { unix-stream("/dev/log"); internal(); udp(ip(0.0.0.0) port(514)); };
				</synopsis>
			</example>
			<para>Each driver may take parameters; some of them are required, others are optional.
				The required parameters are positional, meaning that they must be specified in a
				defined order. A <parameter>unix-stream()</parameter> driver has a single required
				argument, the name of the socket to listen to, and several optional parameters,
				which follow the socket name. Optional arguments can be specified in any order using
				the <literal>option(value)</literal> syntax. </para>
			<para>
				<table>
					<title>Available source drivers in syslog-ng</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Name</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>internal()</entry>
								<entry>Messages generated internally in
									<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>unix-stream()</entry>
								<entry>Opens the specified unix socket in
									<parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> mode and listens for
									messages.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>unix-dgram()</entry>
								<entry>Opens the specified unix socket in
									<parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> mode and listens for
								messages.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>file()</entry>
								<entry>Opens the specified file and reads messages.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>pipe(), fifo</entry>
								<entry>Opens the specified named pipe and reads messages.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>tcp()</entry>
								<entry>Listens on the specified TCP port for messages.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>udp()</entry>
								<entry>Listens on the specified UDP port for messages.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>tcp6()</entry>
								<entry>Listens on the specified TCP port for messages over
								IPv6.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>udp6()</entry>
								<entry>Listens on the specified UDP port for messages over
								IPv6.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>sun-stream(), sun-streams()</entry>
								<entry>Opens the specified <parameter>STREAMS</parameter> device on
									Solaris systems and reads messages.</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</para>
			<para>For a complete descriptions on the above drivers, see <xref
					linkend="reference_sourcedrivers"/>. </para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="filters">
			<title>Filters</title>
			<para>Filters perform log routing within <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>. You can write a
				boolean expression using internal functions: a message passes if the expression is
				true. </para>
			<para>Filters also have a unique identifying name that can be referenced in log
				statements. </para>
			<para>Syntax for the filter statement:</para>
			<synopsis>
				filter &lt;identifier&gt; { expression; };
			</synopsis>
			<para>An expression may contain parentheses, the boolean operators "and", "or" and
				"not", and any of the functions listed in <xref linkend="filterfunc"/>. </para>
			<example>
				<title>A filter statement finding the messages containing the word 'deny' coming
					from the host 'foo'</title>
				<synopsis>
					filter f_blurp_deny { host("foo") and match("deny"); };
				</synopsis>
			</example>
			<para>For a complete description on the above functions, see <xref
					linkend="reference_filters"/>. </para>
			<para>In earlier revisions of syslog-ng there was a special filter identifier,
				"DEFAULT", which matched all not-yet-matched messages. This could make your
				configuration much simpler and easier to manage. This feature was removed in
				syslog-ng 1.5.x, and a more powerful idea was introduced. For more details consult
					<xref linkend="logpath"/>. </para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="destinations">
			<title>Destinations</title>
			<para>A destination is where a log is sent if the filtering rules match. Similarly to
				sources, destinations are comprised of one or more drivers, each defining how
				messages are handled. Destinations can be declared in the configuration file via a
				destination statement using the syntax
				below:<synopsis>
					destination &lt;identifier&gt; { destination-driver(params); destination-driver(params); ... };
				</synopsis>
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>The list of drivers may be empty: in this case all messages sent to the
					destination are discarded. This is equivalent to omitting the destination from
					the log statement.</para>
			</note>
			<table>
				<title>Available destination drivers in syslog-ng</title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Name</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>file()</entry>
							<entry>Writes messages to the specified file.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>fifo(), pipe()</entry>
							<entry>Writes messages to the specified named pipe.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>unix-stream()</entry>
							<entry>Sends messages to the specified unix socket in
									<parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> style (Linux).</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>unix-dgram()</entry>
							<entry>Sends messages to the specified unix socket in
									<parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> style (BSD).</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>tcp()</entry>
							<entry>Sends messages to the specified host and TCP port.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>udp()</entry>
							<entry>Sends messages to the specified host and UDP port.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>tcp6()</entry>
							<entry>Sends messages to the specified host and TCP port over
							IPv6.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>udp6()</entry>
							<entry>Sends messages to the specified host and UDP port over
							IPv6.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>usertty()</entry>
							<entry>Sends messages to the specified user's terminal if logged
							in.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>program()</entry>
							<entry>Forks and launches the specified program, and sends messages to
								its standard input.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			<para>For detailed description of the supported drivers, see <xref
					linkend="reference_destinationdrivers"/>. </para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="templates">
			<title>Template objects</title>
			<para>syslog-ng 2.0 allows you to define common templates, and refer to them from every
				object requiring a template. For example:</para>
			<para>
				<synopsis>
          template t_filetmpl { template("$ISODATE $HOST $MSG\n"); template_escape(no)); };
          
          destination d_file { file("/var/log/messages" template(t_filetmpl); };
        </synopsis>
				Templates can reference one or more macros as described in <xref linkend="macros"/>. </para>
			<note>
				<para>Previous versions of syslog-ng required template formats to be defined for
					every destination.</para>
			</note>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="logpath">
			<title>Log paths</title>
			<para>The previous chapters described how to define sources, filters and destinations.
				These components have to be connected together using log statements. The syntax of
				log statements is described below:</para>
			<synopsis>
				log { source(s1); source(s2); ... 
				filter(f1); filter(f2); ... 
				destination(d1); destination(d2); ... 
				flags(flag1[, flag2...]); };
			</synopsis>
			<para>Any message coming from any of the listed sources, matching all the filters is
				sent to all listed destinations. Log statements are processed in the order they
				appear in the configuration file. </para>
			<para>By default, all matching log statements are processed, therefore a single log
				message might be sent to the same destination several times, provided the
				destination is listed in several log statements. </para>
			<para>This default behavior can be changed using the <parameter>flags()</parameter>
				parameter. <table id="logflags">
					<title>Log statement flags</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Flag</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>final</entry>
								<entry>This flag means that the processing of log statements ends
									here. Note that this does not necessarily mean that matching
									messages will be stored only once, as there can be matching log
									statements processed prior the current one. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>fallback</entry>
								<entry>This flag makes a log statement 'fallback'. Being a fallback
									statement means that only messages not matching any
									'non-fallback' log statements will be dispatched. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>catchall</entry>
								<entry>This flag means that the source of the message is ignored,
									only the filters are taken into account when matching
								messages.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>flow-control</entry>
								<entry>Specifies that this log path should be flow controlled,
									meaning that syslog-ng will stop reading messages from sources
									feeding destinations through this log statement if the
									destinations are not able to process the messages at the
									required speed. If disabled, syslog-ng will drop messages if the
									destination queues are full. If enabled, syslog-ng will only
									drop messages if the destination queues/window sizes are
									improperly sized. </entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</para>

		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="options">
			<title>Options</title>
			<para>There are several options that can modify the behavior of
				<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>. For an exact list of possible options see <xref
					linkend="reference_options"/>. Each option may have parameters, similarly to
				driver specifications. The general syntax is:</para>
			<synopsis>
				options { option1(params); option2(params); ... };
			</synopsis>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="reference">
		<title>Reference</title>
		<para>This chapter documents the drivers and options that can be used in the configuration
			file. </para>
		<sect1 id="reference_sourcedrivers">
			<title>Source drivers</title>
			<para>The following drivers may be used in source statements, as described in <xref
					linkend="sources"/>. The option <link linkend="reference_options">
					<parameter>log_msg_size()</parameter>
				</link> is available in each source: it specifies the maximum length of incoming log
				messages in bytes. If not specified, the value of the global option is used (see
					<xref linkend="reference_options"/>). </para>
			<para>Some parameters affecting message parsing are common for all sources: <table
					id="sourcecommonopts">
					<title>Common options for source drivers</title>
					<tgroup cols="4">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Name</entry>
								<entry>Type</entry>
								<entry>Default</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>flags()</entry>
								<entry>set of [no-parse,kernel]</entry>
								<entry>empty set</entry>
								<entry>Specifies log parsing flags. <parameter>no-parse</parameter>
									completely disables syslog message parsing and processes the
									complete line as the message part of a syslog message. Other
									information (timestamp, host, etc.) is added automatically. This
									flag is useful for parsing files not complying to the syslog
									format. <parameter>kernel</parameter> makes the source default
									to the <parameter>LOG_KERN | LOG_CRIT</parameter> priority if
									not specified otherwise. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>log_msg_size()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>The value specified by the global
									<parameter>log_msg_size()</parameter> option, which defaults to
										<parameter>8192</parameter>.</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the maximum length of incoming log messages. Uses
									the value of the <link linkend="reference_options">global
									option</link> if not specified. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>log_iw_size()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>100</entry>
								<entry>The size of the initial window, this value is used during
									flow control.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>log_fetch_limit()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>The value specified by the global <link
										linkend="reference_options">
										<parameter>log_fetch_limit()</parameter>
									</link> option, which defaults to <parameter>10</parameter>.</entry>
								<entry>The maximum number of messages fetched from a source during a
									single poll loop. The destination queues might fill up before
									flow-control could stop reading if
									<parameter>log_fetch_limit()</parameter> is too high. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>log_prefix()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry/>
								<entry>A string prepended to every log message. It can be used to
									prepend an arbitrary string to any log source, though it is most
									commonly used for adding <parameter>kernel:</parameter> to the
									kernel messages on Linux. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>pad_size()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies input padding. Some operating systems (such as
									HP-UX) pad all 0 messages to block boundary. This option can be
									used to specify the block size. (HP-UX uses 2048 bytes).
									Syslog-ng will pad reads from the associated device to the
									number of bytes set in <parameter>pad_size()</parameter>. Mostly
									used on HP-UX where <filename>/dev/log</filename> is a named
									pipe and every write is padded to 2048 bytes. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>follow_freq()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>-1</entry>
								<entry>Indicates that the source should be checked periodically
									instead of being polled. This is useful for files which always
									indicate readability, even though no new lines were appended. If
									this value is higher than zero, syslog-ng will not attempt to
									use <parameter>poll()</parameter> on the file, but checks
									whether the file changed every time the
									<parameter>follow_freq()</parameter> interval (in seconds) has
									elapsed. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>time_zone()</entry>
								<entry>timezone in the form +/-HH:MM</entry>
								<entry/>
								<entry>The default timezone for messages read from the source.
									Applies only if no timezone is specified within the message
									itself. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>optional()</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry/>
								<entry>Instruct syslog-ng to ignore the error if a specific source
									cannot be initialized. No other attempts to initialize the
									source will be made until the configuration is reloaded. This
									option currently applies to the <parameter>pipe()</parameter>,
										<parameter>unix-dgram</parameter>, and
										<parameter>unix-stream</parameter> drivers.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>keep_timestamp()</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>yes</entry>
								<entry>Specifies whether syslog-ng should accept the timestamp
									received from the peer. If disabled, the time of reception will
									be used instead. </entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</para>
			<sect2>
				<title>internal()</title>
				<para>All internally generated messages "come" from this special source. To collect
					warnings, errors and notices from <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> itself, include
					this source in one of your source statements. </para>
				<synopsis>
					Declaration: internal()
				</synopsis>
				<para><emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> will issue a warning upon startup if this
					driver is not referenced. </para>
				<example>
					<title>Using the internal() driver</title>
					<synopsis>
						source s_local { internal(); };
					</synopsis>
				</example>
			</sect2>
			<sect2>
				<title>unix-stream() and unix-dgram()</title>
				<para>These two drivers behave similarly: they open the given
					<parameter>AF_UNIX</parameter> socket and start listening on it for messages.
						<parameter>unix-stream()</parameter> is primarily used on Linux and uses
						<parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> semantics (connection oriented, no
					messages are lost); while <parameter>unix-dgram()</parameter> is used on BSDs
					and uses <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> semantics: this may result in lost
					local messages if the system is overloaded. </para>
				<para>To avoid denial of service attacks when using connection-oriented protocols,
					the number of simultaneously accepted connections should be limited. This can be
					achieved using the <parameter>max-connections()</parameter> parameter. The
					default value of this parameter is quite strict, you might have to increase it
					on a busy system. </para>
				<para>Both unix-stream and unix-dgram have a single required positional argument,
					specifying the filename of the socket to create, and several optional
					parameters. </para>
				<note>
					<para><parameter>syslogd</parameter> on Linux originally used
							<parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> sockets but this was changed in some
						distributions to <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> at around 1999. The
						change was a fix to a possible DoS problem, however, this might not have
						been a proper solution. On Linux you can choose to use whichever driver you
						like as syslog clients automatically detect the socket type being used. </para>
					<synopsis>
						Declaration: 
						unix-stream(filename [options]);
						unix-dgram(filename [options]); 
					</synopsis>
				</note>
				<para>The following options can be specified for these divers:</para>
				<table>
					<title>Available options for unix-stream() and unix-dgram()</title>
					<tgroup cols="4">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Name</entry>
								<entry>Type</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
								<entry>Default</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>owner()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry>Set the uid of the socket.</entry>
								<entry>root</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>group()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry>Set the gid of the socket.</entry>
								<entry>root</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>perm()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>Set the permission mask. For octal numbers prefix the number
									with '0', e.g.: use 0755 for rwxr-xr-x.</entry>
								<entry>0666</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>keep-alive()</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>Selects whether to keep connections open when
										<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> is restarted; can be used
									only with <parameter>unix-stream()</parameter>. </entry>
								<entry>yes</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>max-connections()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>Limits the number of simultaneously open connections. Can be
									used only with <parameter>unix-stream()</parameter>.</entry>
								<entry>10</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>so_broadcast</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>no</entry>
								<entry>This option controls the <parameter>SO_BROADCAST</parameter>
									socket option required to make syslog-ng send messages to a
									broadcast address. See the <command>socket(7)</command> manual
									page for details. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>so_rcvbuf</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the size of the socket receive buffer in bytes.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>so_sndbuf</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the size of the socket send buffer in bytes.
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
				<example>
					<title>Using the unix-stream() and unix-dgram() drivers</title>
					<synopsis>
						# source declaration on Linux
						source s_stream { unix-stream("/dev/log" max-connections(10)); };
						
						# source declaration on BSD
						source s_dgram { unix-dgram("/var/run/log"); };						
					</synopsis>
				</example>
			</sect2>
			<sect2>
				<title>tcp(), tcp6(), udp() and udp6()</title>
				<para>These drivers enable to receive messages from the network. As the name of the
					drivers implies, both UDP and TCP can be used to transport messages. The
						<parameter>tcp6()</parameter> and <parameter>udp6()</parameter> use the IPv6
					network protocol.</para>
				<para>UDP is a simple datagram oriented protocol, which provides "best effort
					service" to transfer messages between hosts. It may lose messages, and no
					attempt is made at the protocol level to retransmit such lost messages. The
						<emphasis>syslog</emphasis> protocol traditionally uses UDP. </para>
				<para>TCP provides connection-oriented service, which basically means a
					flow-controlled message pipeline. In this pipeline each message is acknowledged,
					and retransmission is done for lost packets. Generally it is safer to use TCP,
					because lost connections can be detected, and no messages get lost, assuming
					that the TCP connection does not break. When a TCP connection is broken the
					'in-transit' messages that were sent by syslog-ng but not yet received on the
					other side are lost. (Basically these messages are still sitting in the socket
					buffer of the sending host and syslog-ng has no information about the fate of
					these messages). </para>
				<para>The <parameter>tcp()</parameter> and <parameter>udp()</parameter> drivers do
					not require any positional parameters. By default they bind to
						<parameter>0.0.0.0:514</parameter>, which means that
					<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> will listen on all available interfaces, port
					514. To limit accepted connections to only one interface, use the
						<parameter>localip()</parameter> parameter as described below. </para>
				<note>
					<para>The tcp port 514 is reserved for use with <command>rshell</command>, so
						select a different port if <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> and
							<command>rshell</command> is used at the same time. </para>
				</note>
				<para>If you specify a multicast bind address to <parameter>udp()</parameter> and
						<parameter>udp6()</parameter>, syslog-ng will automatically join the
					necessary multicast group. TCP does not support multicasting. </para>
				<synopsis>
					Declaration:
					tcp([options]);
					udp([options]);
				</synopsis>
				<para>The following options are valid for <parameter>tcp()</parameter>,
						<parameter>tcp6()</parameter>, <parameter>udp()</parameter>, and
						<parameter>udp6()</parameter>
				</para>
				<table>
					<title>Available options for tcp(), tcp6(), udp(), and udp6()</title>
					<tgroup cols="4">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Name</entry>
								<entry>Type</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
								<entry>Default</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>ip() or localip()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry>The IP address to bind to. Note that this is not the address
									where messages are accepted from. </entry>
								<entry>0.0.0.0</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>port() or localport()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>The port number to bind to.</entry>
								<entry>514</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>keep-alive()</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>Available for <parameter>tcp()</parameter> only; specifies
									whether connections should be closed upon the receipt of a
									SIGHUP signal. </entry>
								<entry>yes</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>tcp-keep-alive()</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>Available for <parameter>tcp()</parameter> only; specifies
									whether TCP keep alive messages using the SO_KEEPALIVE socket
									option should be enabled. </entry>
								<entry>no</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>max-connections()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the maximum number of simultaneous connections.</entry>
								<entry>10</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>so_broadcast</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>no</entry>
								<entry>This option controls the <parameter>SO_BROADCAST</parameter>
									socket option required to make syslog-ng send messages to a
									broadcast address. See the <command>socket(7)</command> manual
									page for details. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>so_rcvbuf</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the size of the socket receive buffer in bytes.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>so_sndbuf</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the size of the socket send buffer in bytes.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>ip_ttl</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the Time-To-Live value of outgoing packets.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>ip_tos</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the Type-of-Service value of outgoing packets.
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
				<example>
					<title>Using the udp() and tcp() drivers</title>
					<synopsis>
						source s_tcp { tcp(ip(127.0.0.1) port(1999) max-connections(10)); };
						source s_udp { udp(); };
					</synopsis>
				</example>
			</sect2>
			<sect2>
				<title>file()</title>
				<para>Usually the kernel presents its messages in a special file
						(<parameter>/dev/kmsg</parameter> on BSDs, <parameter>/proc/kmsg</parameter>
					on Linux), so to read such special files the <parameter>file()</parameter>
					driver is needed. Please note that this driver cannot follow a file like
						<command>tail -f</command> does. To feed a growing logfile into
						<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> (e.g.: an HTTP
					<filename>access.log</filename>), use a script like this: </para>
				<example>
					<title>Script to feed a growing logfile into syslog-ng</title>
					<synopsis>
						#!/bin/sh
						tail -f logfile | logger -p local4.info
					</synopsis>
				</example>
				<para>The file driver has a single required parameter specifying the file to open,
					and has only the common source specific options as specified in <xref
						linkend="sourcecommonopts"/>. </para>
				<synopsis>
					Declaration:
					file(filename);
				</synopsis>
				<example>
					<title>Using the file() driver</title>
					<synopsis>
						source s_file { file("/proc/kmsg" log_prefix("kernel: ")); };
					</synopsis>
				</example>
				<note>
					<para>On Linux, the <parameter>klogd</parameter> daemon can be used in addition
						to <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> to read kernel messages and forward them
						to <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>. <parameter>klogd</parameter> used to
						preprocess kernel messages to resolve symbols etc., but as this is
						deprecated by <parameter>ksymoops</parameter> there is really no point in
						running both <parameter>klogd</parameter> and <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>
						in parallel. Also note that running two processes reading
							<filename>/proc/kmsg</filename> at the same time might result in
						dead-locks. </para>
				</note>
			</sect2>
			<sect2>
				<title>pipe()</title>
				<para>The pipe driver opens a named pipe with the specified name and listens for
					messages. It is used as the native message delivery protocol on HP-UX. </para>
				<para>The pipe driver has a single required parameter, specifying the filename of
					the pipe to open. It has only the common source specific options as specified in
						<xref linkend="sourcecommonopts"/>. </para>
				<para>Pipe is very similar to the <parameter>file()</parameter> driver, but there
					are a few differences, for example <parameter>pipe()</parameter> opens its
					argument in read-write mode, therefore it is not recommended to be used on
					special files like <filename>/proc/kmsg</filename>.</para>
				<warning>
					<para>It is not recommended to use <parameter>pipe()</parameter> on anything
						else than real pipes. </para>
				</warning>
				<synopsis>
					Declaration:
					pipe(filename);
				</synopsis>
				<note>
					<para>You have to create this pipe using <command>mkfifo(1)</command>. </para>
				</note>
				<example>
					<title>Using the pipe() driver</title>
					<synopsis>
						source s_pipe { pipe("/dev/log" pad_size(2048)); };
					</synopsis>
				</example>
			</sect2>
			<sect2>
				<title>sun-streams() driver</title>
				<para>Solaris uses its <parameter>STREAMS</parameter> framework to send messages to
					the <parameter>syslogd</parameter> process. <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> has
					to be compiled with this driver enabled for <parameter>sun-streams()</parameter>
					to be usable (see <command>./configure --help</command>). </para>
				<para>Newer versions of Solaris (2.5.1 and above), use a new IPC in addition to
						<parameter>STREAMS</parameter>, called door to confirm the delivery of a
					message. <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> supports this new IPC mechanism via the
						<parameter>door()</parameter> option (see below). </para>
				<para>The <parameter>sun-streams()</parameter> driver has a single required argument
					specifying the <parameter>STREAMS</parameter> device to open, and the
						<parameter>door()</parameter> option.</para>
				<example>
					<title>Using the sun-streams() driver</title>
					<synopsis>
						source s_stream { sun-streams("/dev/log" door("/etc/.syslog_door"); };
					</synopsis>
				</example>
				<table>
					<title>Available options for sun-streams</title>
					<tgroup cols="4">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Name</entry>
								<entry>Type</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
								<entry>Default</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>door()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the filename of a door to open, needed on Solaris
									above 2.5.1. </entry>
								<entry>none</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="reference_destinationdrivers">
			<title>Destination drivers</title>
			<para>Destination drivers output log messages to somewhere outside
				<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>: a file or a network socket. </para>
			<para>Some of the parameters affecting message formatting and sending are common for all
				destinations.</para>
			<table id="destcommonopts">
				<title>Common options for destination drivers</title>
				<tgroup cols="4">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Name</entry>
							<entry>Type</entry>
							<entry>Default</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>flags()</entry>
							<entry/>
							<entry>empty set</entry>
							<entry> </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>log_fifo_size()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>Use global setting. </entry>
							<entry>The number of entries in the output fifo. </entry>
						</row>

						<row>
							<entry>fsync()</entry>
							<entry>yes or no</entry>
							<entry>no</entry>
							<entry>Forces an <parameter>fsync()</parameter> call on the destination
								fd after each write. Note: this may seriously degrade
							performance.</entry>
						</row>

						<row>
							<entry>sync_freq()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>Use global setting. </entry>
							<entry>This setting is an obsolete alias of the
								<parameter>flush_lines()</parameter> option. </entry>
						</row>

						<row>
							<entry>flush_lines()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>Use global setting. </entry>
							<entry>Specifies how many lines are flushed to a destination at a time.
								Syslog-ng waits for this number of lines to accumulate and sends
								them off in a single batch. Setting this number high increases
								throughput as fully filled frames are sent to the network, but also
								increases message latency. The latency can be limited by the use of
								the <parameter>flush_timeout</parameter> option. </entry>
						</row>

						<row>
							<entry>flush_timeout()</entry>
							<entry>time in milliseconds</entry>
							<entry>Use global setting. </entry>
							<entry>Specifies the time syslog-ng waits for lines to accumulate in its
								output buffer. See the <parameter>flush_lines</parameter> option for
								more information. </entry>
						</row>

						<row>
							<entry>template()</entry>
							<entry>string</entry>
							<entry>A format conforming to the default logfile format. </entry>
							<entry>Specifies a template defining the logformat to be used in the
								destination. Macros are described in <xref linkend="macros"/>.
								Please note that for network destinations it might not be
								appropriate to change the template as it changes the on-wire format
								of the syslog protocol which might not be tolerated by stock syslog
								receivers (like <parameter>syslogd</parameter> or syslog-ng itself).
								For network destinations make sure the receiver can cope with the
								custom format defined. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>template_escape()</entry>
							<entry>yes or no</entry>
							<entry>yes</entry>
							<entry>Turns on escaping <parameter>'</parameter> and
								<parameter>"</parameter> in templated output files. This is useful
								for generating SQL statements and quoting string contents so that
								parts of the log message are not interpreted as commands to the SQL
								server.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>timezone()</entry>
							<entry>timezone offset in seconds</entry>
							<entry>unspecified </entry>
							<entry>Convert timestamps to the timezone specified by this option. If
								this option is not set then the original timezone information in the
								message is used. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>ts_format()</entry>
							<entry>rfc3164, bsd, rfc3339, iso</entry>
							<entry>rfc3164</entry>
							<entry>Override the global timestamp format (set in the global
									<parameter>ts_format()</parameter> parameter) for the specific
								destination. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>frac_digits()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>0</entry>
							<entry><emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> can store fractions of a second in
								the timestamps. <parameter>frac_digits()</parameter> specifies the
								number of digits stored. The digits storing the fractions are padded
								by zeros if the original timestamp of the message specifies only
								seconds. Fractions can always be stored for the time the message was
								received.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			<note>
				<para>The <parameter>usertty</parameter> destination does not support
				templates.</para>
			</note>
			<sect2>
				<title>file()</title>
				<para>The file driver is one of the most important destination drivers in
						<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>. It allows to output messages to the
					specified file, or to a set of files. </para>
				<para>The destination filename may include macros which get expanded when the
					message is written, thus a simple <parameter>file()</parameter> driver may crete
					several files. For more information on available macros see <xref
						linkend="macros"/>. </para>
				<para>If the expanded filename refers to a directory which does not exist, it will
					be created depending on the <parameter>create_dirs()</parameter> setting (both
					global and a per destination option).</para>
				<warning>
					<para>Since the state of each created file must be tracked by
							<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>, it consumes some memory for each file.
						If no new messages are written to a file within 60 seconds (controlled by
						the <parameter>time_reap</parameter> global option), it is closed, and its
						state is freed. </para>
					<para>Exploiting this, a DoS attack can be mounted against the system. If the
						number of possible destination files and its needed memory is more than the
						amount available on the logserver. </para>
					<para>The most suspicious macro is <parameter>$PROGRAM</parameter>, where the
						number of possible variations is quite high, so in untrusted environments
							<parameter>$PROGRAM</parameter> should not be used. </para>
				</warning>
				<para>Apart from the common destination options described in <xref
						linkend="destcommonopts"/> the <parameter>file()</parameter> destination has
					the following options:</para>
				<table>
					<title>Available options for file()</title>
					<tgroup cols="4">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Name</entry>
								<entry>Type</entry>
								<entry>Default</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<!--							<row>
								<entry>encrypt()</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>Use global setting. </entry>
								<entry>Encrypt the resulting file. NOTE:  not implemented yet. </entry>
							</row>-->
							<!--							<row>
								<entry>compress()</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>Use global setting. </entry>
								<entry>Compress the resulting logfile using zlib. NOTE: not
									implemented yet. </entry>
							</row>-->
							<row>
								<entry>owner()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry>Set the owner of the created file to the one specified. </entry>
								<entry>root</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>group()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry>Set the group of the created file to the one specified. </entry>
								<entry>root</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>perm()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>The permission mask of the file if it is created by
										<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>. For octal numbers prefix the
									number with '0', e.g.: use 0755 for rwxr-xr-x. </entry>
								<entry> 0600 </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>create_dirs()</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>Enable creating non-existing directories. </entry>
								<entry> no </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>dir_perm()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>The permission mask of directories created by
										<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>. Log directories are only
									created if a file after macro expansion refers to a non-existing
									directory, and directory creation is enabled (see the
										<parameter>create_dirs()</parameter> option below). For
									octal numbers prefix the number with '0', e.g.: use 0755 for
									rwxr-xr-x.</entry>
								<entry> 0600 </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>dir_owner()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry>The owner of directories created by
									<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>. </entry>
								<entry> root </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>dir_group()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry>The group of directories created by
									<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>. </entry>
								<entry> root </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>remove_if_older()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>If set to a value higher than 0, before writing to a file,
									syslog-ng checks whether this file is older than the specified
									amount of time (specified in seconds). If so, it removes the
									existing file and the line to be written is the first line of a
									new file having the same name. In combination with e.g.: the
										<parameter>$WEEKDAY</parameter> macro, this can be used for
									simple log rotation, in case not all history has to be kept. </entry>
								<entry>Never remove existing files; use append instead ( = 0).
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
				<example>
					<title>Using the file() driver</title>
					<synopsis>
						destination d_file { file("/var/log/messages" ); };
					</synopsis>
				</example>
				<example>
					<title>Using the file() driver with macros in the file name and a template for
						the message</title>
					<synopsis>
						destination d_file {
						file("/var/log/$YEAR.$MONTH.$DAY/messages"
						template("$HOUR:$MIN:$SEC $TZ $HOST [$LEVEL] $MSG $MSG\n")
						template_escape(no)
						);
						};
					</synopsis>
				</example>
			</sect2>
			<sect2>
				<title>pipe()</title>
				<para>This driver sends messages to a named pipe like
					<filename>/dev/xconsole</filename>. </para>
				<para>The pipe driver has a single required parameter, specifying the filename of
					the pipe to open. </para>
				<synopsis>
					Declaration:
					pipe(filename);
				</synopsis>
				<note>
					<para>You have to create this pipe using <command>mkfifo(1)</command>. </para>
				</note>
				<para>Apart from the common destination options described in <xref
						linkend="destcommonopts"/> the <parameter>pipe()</parameter> destination has
					the following options:</para>
				<table>
					<title>Available options for pipe()</title>
					<tgroup cols="4">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Name</entry>
								<entry>Type</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
								<entry>Default</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>owner()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry>Set the owner of the pipe to the one specified. </entry>
								<entry> root </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>group()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry>Set the group of the pipe to the one specified. </entry>
								<entry> root </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>perm()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>The permission mask of the pipe. For octal numbers prefix the
									number with '0', e.g.: use 0755 for rwxr-xr-x. </entry>
								<entry> 0600 </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>template()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry>Specifies a template which defines the logformat to be used.
									Possible macros are the same as for the
									<parameter>file()</parameter> destination. </entry>
								<entry>A format conforming to the default logfile format. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>template_escape()</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>Turns on escaping ' and " in templated output files. This is
									useful for generating SQL statements and quoting string contents
									so that parts of the log message are not interpreted as commands
									to the SQL server.</entry>
								<entry> yes </entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
				<example>
					<title>Using the pipe() driver</title>
					<synopsis>
						destination d_pipe { pipe("/dev/xconsole"); };
					</synopsis>
				</example>
			</sect2>
			<sect2>
				<title>unix-stream() &amp; unix-dgram()</title>
				<para>This driver sends messages to a unix socket in either
					<parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> or <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> mode. </para>
				<para>Both drivers have a single required argument specifying the name of the socket
					to connect to. </para>
				<synopsis>
					Declaration: 
					unix-stream(filename [options]);
					unix-dgram(filename [options]); 
				</synopsis>
				<para>Apart from the common destination options described in <xref
						linkend="destcommonopts"/> the <parameter>unix-stream()</parameter> and
						<parameter>unix-dgram()</parameter> destinations has the following options:</para>
				<table>
					<title>Available options for unix-stream() and unix-dgram()</title>
					<tgroup cols="4">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Name</entry>
								<entry>Type</entry>
								<entry>Default</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>so_broadcast</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>no</entry>
								<entry>This option controls the <parameter>SO_BROADCAST</parameter>
									socket option required to make syslog-ng send messages to a
									broadcast address. See the <command>socket(7)</command> manual
									page for details. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>so_rcvbuf</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the size of the socket receive buffer in bytes.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>so_sndbuf</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the size of the socket send buffer in bytes.
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
				<example>
					<title>Using the unix-stream() driver</title>
					<synopsis>
						destination d_unix_stream { unix-stream("/var/run/logs"); };
					</synopsis>
				</example>
			</sect2>
			<sect2>
				<title>udp(), udp6(), tcp() and tcp6()</title>
				<para>This driver sends messages to another host on the local intranet or internet
					using either UDP or TCP protocol. The <parameter>tcp6()</parameter> and
						<parameter>udp6()</parameter> drivers use the IPv6 network protocol.</para>
				<para>Both drivers have a single required argument specifying the destination host
					address, where messages should be sent, and several optional parameters. Note
					that this differs from source drivers, where local bind address is implied, and
					none of the parameters are required. </para>
				<para><parameter>udp()</parameter> and <parameter>udp6()</parameter> automatically
					send multicast packets if a multicast destination address is specified.
						<parameter>tcp()</parameter> and <parameter>tcp6()</parameter> do not
					support multicasting.</para>
				<synopsis>
					Declaration:
					tcp(host [options]);
					udp(host [options]);
					tcp6(host [options]);
					udp6(host [options]);					
				</synopsis>
				<para>Apart from the common destination options described in <xref
						linkend="destcommonopts"/> these destinations have the following options:</para>
				<table>
					<title>Available options for udp(), udp6(), tcp() and tcp6()</title>
					<tgroup cols="4">
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Name</entry>
								<entry>Type</entry>
								<entry>Default</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>localip()</entry>
								<entry>string</entry>
								<entry>The IP address to bind to before connecting to target. </entry>
								<entry>0.0.0.0</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>localport()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>The port number to bind to.</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>port() or destport()</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>The port number to connect to.</entry>
								<entry>514</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>spoof_source</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>Enables source address spoofing. This means that the host
									running <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> generates UDP packets
									with the source IP address matching the original sender of the
									message. It is useful when you want to perform some kind of
									preprocessing via syslog-ng then forward messages to your
									central log management solution with the source address of the
									original sender. This option only works for UDP destinations
									though the original message can be received by TCP as well. This
									option is only available if <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> was
									compiled using the <parameter>--enable-spoof-source</parameter>
									configure option. </entry>
								<entry>no</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>so_broadcast</entry>
								<entry>yes or no</entry>
								<entry>no</entry>
								<entry>This option controls the <parameter>SO_BROADCAST</parameter>
									socket option required to make syslog-ng send messages to a
									broadcast address. See the <command>socket(7)</command> manual
									page for details. </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>so_rcvbuf</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the size of the socket receive buffer in bytes.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>so_sndbuf</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the size of the socket send buffer in bytes.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>ip_ttl</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the Time-To-Live value of outgoing packets.
								</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>ip_tos</entry>
								<entry>number</entry>
								<entry>0</entry>
								<entry>Specifies the Type-of-Service value of outgoing packets.
								</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
				<example>
					<title>Using the tcp() driver</title>
					<synopsis>
						destination d_tcp { tcp("10.1.2.3" port(1999); localport(999)); };
					</synopsis>
				</example>
			</sect2>

			<sect2>
				<title>usertty()</title>
				<para>This driver writes messages to the terminal of a logged-in user. </para>
				<para>The <parameter>usertty()</parameter> driver has a single required argument,
					specifying a username who should receive a copy of matching messages. </para>
				<synopsis>
					Declaration: 
					usertty(username);
				</synopsis>
				<para><parameter>usertty()</parameter> has only the common destination options
					described in <xref linkend="destcommonopts"/>.</para>
				<note>
					<para>The <parameter>usertty()</parameter> destination does not support
						templates.</para>
				</note>
				<example>
					<title>Using the usertty() driver</title>
					<synopsis>
						destination d_usertty { usertty("root"); };
					</synopsis>
				</example>
			</sect2>

			<sect2>
				<title>program()</title>
				<para>This driver executes the specified program with the specified arguments and
					sends messages to the standard input (<parameter>stdin</parameter>) of the
					child. </para>
				<para>The <parameter>program()</parameter> driver has a single required parameter,
					specifying a program name to start. The program is executed with the help of the
					current shell, so the command may include both file patterns and I/O
					redirection, they will be processed. </para>
				<synopsis>
					Declaration: 
					program(commandtorun);
				</synopsis>
				<note>
					<para>Syslog-ng 1.6 executed the program once at startup, and kept it running
						until SIGHUP or exit. The reason was to prevent starting up a large number
						of programs for messages, which would have enabled an easy DoS attack. </para>
					<para>Syslog-ng 2.0 on the other hand restarts the program if it exits, mainly
						for reliability reasons. However it is not recommended to launch programs
						for single messages as that might easily cause a DoS for the system. </para>
				</note>

				<para>The program destination supports all common destination options described in
						<xref linkend="destcommonopts"/>.
                                      The default message format that is
                                      sent to the program matches the BSD syslog protocol, e.g. it includes 
                                      the priority value in addition to the format used in logfiles.</para>
				<example>
					<title>Using the program() destination driver</title>
					<synopsis>
						destination d_prg { program("/bin/cat >/dev/null"); };
					</synopsis>
				</example>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="reference_filters">
			<title>Filter functions</title>
			<para>The following functions may be used in the filter statement, as described in <xref
					linkend="filters"/>.</para>
			<table id="filterfunc">
				<title>Available filter functions in syslog-ng</title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Name</entry>
							<entry>Synopsis</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>facility</entry>
							<entry>facility(facility[,facility])</entry>
							<entry>Match messages having one of the listed facility code. An
								alternate syntax permits the use an arbitrary facility
							codes.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>facility</entry>
							<entry>facility(&lt;numeric facility code&gt;)</entry>
							<entry>An alternate syntax for <parameter>facility</parameter>
								permitting the use of an arbitrary facility code. Facility codes
								0-23 are predefined and can be referenced by their usual name.
								Facility codes above 24 are not defined but can be used by this
								alternate syntax. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>level() or priority()</entry>
							<entry>level(pri[,pri1..pri2[,pri3]])</entry>
							<entry>Match messages based on priority.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>program()</entry>
							<entry>program(regexp)</entry>
							<entry>Match messages by using a regular expression against the program
								name field of log messages </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>host()</entry>
							<entry>host(regexp)</entry>
							<entry>Match messages by using a regular expression against the hostname
								field of log messages. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>match()</entry>
							<entry>match(regexp)</entry>
							<entry>Tries to match a regular expression to the message
							itself.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>filter()</entry>
							<entry>filter(filtername)</entry>
							<entry>Call another filter rule and evaluate its value.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>netmask()</entry>
							<entry>netmask(ip/mask)</entry>
							<entry>Check the sender's IP address whether it is in the specified IP
								subnet.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="macros">
			<title>Macros</title>
			<para>Certain parts of syslog-ng (e.g.: destination filenames and message content
				templates) can refer to one or more macros, which get expanded as a message is
				processed. The table below summarizes the macros available in syslog-ng. </para>
			<para>Macros can be included by prefixing the macro name with a <parameter>$</parameter>
				sign, just like in Bourne compatible shells. syslog-ng 2.0 uses a new syntax for
				braces around macro names: <parameter>"$MSG"</parameter> and
				<parameter>"${MSG}"</parameter> are equivalent. </para>
			<para>The macros related to the time of the message (e.g.:
				<parameter>ISODATE</parameter>, <parameter>HOUR</parameter>, etc.) have two further
				versions each: one with the <parameter>S_</parameter> and one with the
				<parameter>R_</parameter> prefix (e.g.: <parameter>S_DATE</parameter> and
					<parameter>R_DATE</parameter> ). The <parameter>S_DATE</parameter> macro
				represents the date found in the log message, i.e. when the message was sent by the
				original application. <parameter>R_DATE</parameter> is the date when syslog has
				received the message. <parameter>DATE</parameter> equals either
				<parameter>S_DATE</parameter> or <parameter>R_DATE</parameter>, depending on the
				global option set in the now deprecated <parameter>use_time_recvd()</parameter>
				parameter (see <xref linkend="reference_options"/>). </para>
			<table>
				<title>Available macros in filename expansion</title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Name</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>FACILITY</entry>
							<entry>The name of the facility from where the message originates.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>PRIORITY or LEVEL</entry>
							<entry>The priority of the message. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>TAG</entry>
							<entry>The priority and facility encoded as a 2 digit hexadecimal
								number. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>PRI</entry>
							<entry>The priority and facility encoded as a 2 or 3 digit decimal
								number as it is present in syslog messages. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>DATE, R_DATE, S_DATE</entry>
							<entry>Date of the message using the BSD-syslog style timestamp format
								(month/day/hour/minute/second, each expressed in two digits). This
								is the original syslog time stamp without year information, e.g.:
									<parameter>Jun 13 15:58:00</parameter>. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>FULLDATE, R_FULLDATE, S_FULLDATE</entry>
							<entry>A nonstandard format for the date of the message using the same
								format as <parameter>DATE</parameter>, but including the year as
								well, e.g.: <parameter>2006 Jun 13 15:58:00</parameter>.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>ISODATE, R_ISODATE, S_ISODATE</entry>
							<entry>Date of the message in the ISO 8601 compatible standard timestamp
								format (yyyy-mm-ddThh:mm:ss+-ZONE), e.g.:
									<parameter>2006-06-13T15:58:00.123+01:00</parameter>. If
								possible, it is recommended to use <parameter>ISODATE</parameter>
								for timestamping. Note that syslog-ng can produce fractions of a
								second in the timestamp by using the
								<parameter>frac_digits()</parameter> global or per-destination
								option.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>STAMP, R_STAMP, S_STAMP</entry>
							<entry>A timestamp formatted according to the <link
									linkend="reference_options">
									<parameter>ts_format()</parameter>
								</link> global or per-destination option.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>YEAR, R_YEAR, S_YEAR</entry>
							<entry>The year the message was sent. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>MONTH, R_MONTH, S_MONTH</entry>
							<entry>The month the message was sent. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>DAY, R_DAY, S_DAY</entry>
							<entry>The day the message was sent. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>WEEKDAY, R_WEEKDAY, S_WEEKDAY</entry>
							<entry>The 3-letter name of the day of week the message was sent, e.g.
									<parameter>Thu</parameter>. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>WEEK, R_WEEK, S_WEEK</entry>
							<entry>The week number of the year. (The first Monday in the year marks
								the first week.)</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>HOUR, R_HOUR, S_HOUR</entry>
							<entry>The hour of day the message was sent. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>MIN, R_MIN, S_MIN</entry>
							<entry>The minute the message was sent. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>SEC, R_SEC, S_SEC</entry>
							<entry>The second the message was sent. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>UNIXTIME, R_UNIXTIME, S_UNIXTIME</entry>
							<entry>Standard unix timestamp, represented as the number of seconds
								since <parameter>1970-01-01T00:00:00</parameter>. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>TZOFFSET, R_TZOFFSET, S_TZOFFSET</entry>
							<entry>The time-zone as hour offset from GMT; e.g.:
								<parameter>-07:00</parameter>. In syslog-ng 1.6.x this used to be
									<parameter>-0700</parameter> but as
								<parameter>ISODATE</parameter> requires the colon it was added to
									<parameter>TZOFFSET</parameter> as well. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>TZ, R_TZ, S_TZ</entry>
							<entry>Equivalent to TZOFFSET, used to mean the time zone name
								abbreviation in syslog-ng 1.6.x. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>HOST</entry>
							<entry>The name of the source host where the message originates from. If
								the message traverses several hosts and the
									<parameter>chain_hostnames()</parameter> option is on (see <xref
									linkend="reference_options"/>), the first host in the chain is
								used.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>FULLHOST</entry>
							<entry>The full FQDN of the host name chain (without trimming chained
								hosts), including the domain name.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>HOST_FROM</entry>
							<entry>Name of the host that sent the message to
								<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>, as resolved by syslog-ng using DNS.
								If the message traverses several hosts, this is the last host in the
								chain. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>FULLHOST_FROM</entry>
							<entry>FQDN of the host that sent the message to
								<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> as resolved by syslog-ng using DNS.
								If the message traverses several hosts, this is the last host in the
								chain. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>SOURCEIP</entry>
							<entry>IP address of the host that sent the message to
									<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>. (I.e. the IP address of the host
								in the <parameter>FULLHOST_FROM</parameter> macro.) Please note that
								when a message traverses several relays, this macro contains the IP
								of the last relay. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>PROGRAM</entry>
							<entry>The name of the program sending the message. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>PID</entry>
							<entry>The PID of the program sending the message. </entry>
						</row>

						<row>
							<entry>MSG or MESSAGE</entry>
							<entry>Message contents including the program name and pid. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>MSGONLY</entry>
							<entry>Message contents without the program name. </entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="reference_options">
			<title>Options</title>
			<para>The following options can be specified in the options statement, as described in
					<xref linkend="options"/>.</para>
			<table>
				<title>List of global options supported in syslog-ng</title>
				<tgroup cols="3">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Name</entry>
							<entry>Accepted values</entry>
							<entry>Default</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>time_reopen()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>The time to wait in seconds before a dead connection is
								reestablished.</entry>
							<entry>60</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>time_reap()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>The time to wait in seconds before an idle destination file is
								closed.</entry>
							<entry>60</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>time_sleep()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>0</entry>
							<entry>The time to wait in milliseconds between each invocation of the
									<parameter>poll()</parameter> iteration.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>sync() or sync_freq() (DEPRECATED)</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>0</entry>
							<entry>Obsolete aliases for <parameter>flush_lines()</parameter></entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>mark_freq()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>1200</entry>
							<entry>The number of seconds between two <parameter>MARK</parameter>
								lines. <parameter>MARK</parameter> lines are generated if there was
								no message traffic to inform the receiver that the connection is
								still alive. </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>stats_freq()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>600</entry>
							<entry>The period between two STATS messages in seconds. STATS are log
								messages sent by <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis>, containing
								statistics about dropped log messages. This parameter is identical
								to the <parameter>stats()</parameter> option of <emphasis>syslog-ng
									1.6</emphasis>. In <emphasis>syslog-ng 2.0</emphasis>,
									<parameter>stats()</parameter> is an alias of
									<parameter>stats_freq()</parameter>.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>log_fifo_size()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>100</entry>
							<entry>The number of lines fitting to the output queue</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>chain_hostnames()</entry>
							<entry>yes or no</entry>
							<entry>yes</entry>
							<entry>Enable or disable the chained hostname format.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>normalize_hostnames()</entry>
							<entry>yes or no</entry>
							<entry>no</entry>
							<entry>Normalize hostnames, which currently translates to converting
								them to lower case. (requires 1.9.9)</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>keep_hostname()</entry>
							<entry>yes or no</entry>
							<entry>no</entry>
							<entry>Enable or disable hostname rewriting.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>check_hostname()</entry>
							<entry>yes or no</entry>
							<entry>no</entry>
							<entry>Enable or disable checking whether the hostname contains valid
								characters.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>bad_hostname()</entry>
							<entry>regular expression</entry>
							<entry>no</entry>
							<entry>A regexp containing hostnames which should not be handled as
								hostnames. </entry>
						</row>

						<row>
							<entry>create_dirs()</entry>
							<entry>yes or no</entry>
							<entry>no</entry>
							<entry>Enable or disable directory creation for destination
							files.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>owner()</entry>
							<entry>userid</entry>
							<entry>root</entry>
							<entry>The default owner of output files.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>group()</entry>
							<entry>groupid</entry>
							<entry>root</entry>
							<entry>The default group of output files.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>perm()</entry>
							<entry>permission value</entry>
							<entry>0600</entry>
							<entry>The default permission for output files.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>dir_owner()</entry>
							<entry>userid</entry>
							<entry>root</entry>
							<entry>The default owner of newly created directories.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>dir_group()</entry>
							<entry>groupid</entry>
							<entry>root</entry>
							<entry>The default group for newly created directories.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>dir_perm()</entry>
							<entry>permission value</entry>
							<entry>0700</entry>
							<entry>The default permission for newly created directories.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>use_time_recvd() (DEPRECATED)</entry>
							<entry>yes or no</entry>
							<entry>no</entry>
							<entry>
								<para>This option controls how the time related macros are expanded
									in filename and content templates. If set to yes, then the
									non-prefixed versions of the time related macros (e.g.:
										<parameter>HOUR</parameter> instead of
									<parameter>R_HOUR</parameter> and <parameter>S_HOUR</parameter>)
									refer to the time when the message was received, otherwise it
									refers to the timestamp which is in the message. </para>
								<note>
									<para>The timestamps in the messages are generated by the
										originating host and might not be accurate. </para>
								</note>
								<note>
									<para>This option is deprecated as many users assumed that it
										controls the timestamp as it is written to
										logfiles/destinations, which is not the case. To change how
										messages are formatted, specify a content-template referring
										to the appropriate prefixed (<parameter>S_</parameter> or
											<parameter>R_</parameter>) time macro. </para>
								</note>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>ts_format()</entry>
							<entry>rfc3164, bsd, rfc3339, iso</entry>
							<entry>rfc3164</entry>
							<entry>Specifies the timestamp format used when syslog-ng itself formats
								a timestamp and nothing else specifies a format (e.g.:
									<parameter>STAMP</parameter> macros, internal messages, messages
								without original timestamps). </entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>use_dns()</entry>
							<entry>yes or no</entry>
							<entry>yes</entry>
							<entry>Enable or disable DNS usage. syslog-ng blocks on DNS queries, so
								enabling DNS may lead to a Denial of Service attack. To prevent DoS,
								protect your syslog-ng network endpoint with firewall rules, and
								make sure that all hosts which may get to syslog-ng are
							resolvable.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>dns_cache()</entry>
							<entry>yes or no</entry>
							<entry>yes</entry>
							<entry>Enable or disable DNS cache usage.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>dns_cache_size()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>1007</entry>
							<entry>Number of hostnames in the DNS cache.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>dns_cache_expire()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>3600</entry>
							<entry>Number of seconds while a successful lookup is cached.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>dns_cache_expire_failed()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>60</entry>
							<entry>Number of seconds while a failed lookup is cached.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>log_msg_size()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>8192</entry>
							<entry>Maximum length of a message in bytes.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>use_fqdn()</entry>
							<entry>yes or no</entry>
							<entry>no</entry>
							<entry>Add Fully Qualified Domain Name instead of short
							hostname.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>gc_idle_threshold() (DEPRECATED)</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>n/a</entry>
							<entry>Has no meaning in syslog-ng 1.9.x and later. </entry>
						</row>

						<row>
							<entry>gc_busy_threshold() (DEPRECATED)</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>n/a</entry>
							<entry>Has no meaning in syslog-ng 1.9.x and later. </entry>
						</row>

						<row>
							<entry>flush_lines()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>0</entry>
							<entry>Specifies how many lines are flushed to a destination at a time.
								Syslog-ng waits for this number of lines to accumulate and sends
								them off in a single batch. Setting this number high increases
								throughput as fully filled frames are sent to the network, but also
								increases message latency. The latency can be limited by the use of
								the <parameter>flush_timeout</parameter> option. </entry>
						</row>

						<row>
							<entry>flush_timeout()</entry>
							<entry>time in milliseconds</entry>
							<entry>10000</entry>
							<entry>Specifies the time syslog-ng waits for lines to accumulate in its
								output buffer. See the <parameter>flush_lines()</parameter> option
								for more information. </entry>
						</row>

						<row>
							<entry>recv_time_zone()</entry>
							<entry>time offset (e.g.: <parameter>+03:00</parameter>)</entry>
							<entry>local timezone</entry>
							<entry>Specifies the time zone associated with the incoming messages, if
								not specified otherwise in the message or in the source driver. See
									<xref linkend="timezone_handling"/> for details.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>send_time_zone()</entry>
							<entry>time offset (e.g.: <parameter>+03:00</parameter>)</entry>
							<entry>local timezone</entry>
							<entry>Specifies the time zone associated with the messages sent by
								syslog-ng, if not specified otherwise in the message or in the
								destination driver. See <xref linkend="timezone_handling"/> for
								details.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>frac_digits()</entry>
							<entry>number</entry>
							<entry>0</entry>
							<entry><emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> can store fractions of a second in
								the timestamps. <parameter>frac_digits()</parameter> specifies the
								number of digits stored. The digits storing the fractions are padded
								by zeros if the original timestamp of the message specifies only
								seconds. Fractions can always be stored for the received time of the
								messages.</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	<chapter id="tuning">
		<title>Performance tuning in syslog-ng</title>

		<!--<note>
			<para>This information is out of date for syslog-ng 2.0. Some of it might still apply,
				but syslog-ng has changed considerably.</para>
		</note>-->
		<para>There are several settings available you can finetune the behaviour of syslog-ng. The
			defaults should be adequate for a single server or workstation installation, but for a
			central loghost receiving the logs from multiple computers it may not be enough. </para>
		<sect1>
			<title>Setting garbage collector parameters</title>
			<para>Syslog-ng 2.0 is a complete reimplementation of syslog-ng 1.6, and does not use
				the mark and sweep garbage collector at all. The garbage collector parameters
					(<parameter>gc_idle_threshold</parameter>,
				<parameter>gc_busy_threshold</parameter>) are still accepted but are ignored.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Setting time_sleep()</title>
			<para>When there are a lot of parallel connections to syslog-ng, the amount of time
				required to prepare for a single poll loop iteration is significant. Since the
				arrival of every single log message triggers a new iteration, the CPU usage of
				syslog-ng might increase significantly even if the number of messages received is
				otherwise low. The solution is to add a fixed latency to message processing to wait
				some messages to arrive and to process them in blocks. This can be accomplished by
				setting the <parameter>time_sleep()</parameter> to a non-zero value. It is not
				recommended to increase it above 100ms, as that might skew timestamps, slow
				syslog-ng, and cause messages to be dropped. An alternative solution is to avoid
					<parameter>tcp()</parameter> and <parameter>unix-stream()</parameter> sources
				and use the DGRAM versions, <parameter>udp()</parameter> and
				<parameter>unix-dgram()</parameter>, respectively. </para>
			<para>The value of <parameter>fetch_limit()</parameter> and
				<parameter>log_fifo_size()</parameter> must also be sized accordingly when
					<parameter>time_sleep()</parameter> is modified. </para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Setting output queue size</title>
			<para><emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> always reads its incoming log channels to prevent
				the running daemons from blocking. This may result in lost messages if the output
				queue is full, it is therefore important to set the output queue size (termed in
				number of messages). The size of the output queue can be set either globally, or on
				a per destination basis.</para>
			<note>
				<para>This does not apply to syslog-ng 2.0 if the flow-control flag is enabled. See
						<xref linkend="logflags"/> for details.</para>
			</note>
			<synopsis>
			options { log_fifo_size(1000); };
			</synopsis>
			<para>or</para>
			<synopsis>
				destination d_messages { file("/var/log/messages" log_fifo_size(1000)); };
			</synopsis>
			<para>You should set your fifo size to the estimated number of messages in a message
				burst. If bursts extend the bandwidth of your destination pipe,
				<emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> can feed messages into the destination pipe after the
				burst has collapsed. </para>
			<para>Of course <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> cannot widen the network bandwidth, so if
				the destination host lives on a noisy network and the logtraffic extends the
				bandwidth of this network, <emphasis>syslog-ng</emphasis> cannot do anything.
				However, it will do its best. </para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>Setting the sync parameter</title>
			<para>The <parameter>sync</parameter> parameter does not exactly do what its name
				implies. As you have seen messages to be sent are buffered in an output queue. The
					<parameter>sync</parameter> parameter specifies the number of messages held in
				this buffer before anything is written. </para>
			<para>Note that it does not write all buffered messages into a single chunk; each
				distinct message is written with a single <parameter>write()</parameter> system
				call. </para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

</book>
